Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ records, 1812-2019.
Congregational Library & Archives
Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ records, 1812-2019.
RG0150
Congregational Library & Archives
8.91 Cubic Feet
(9 boxes)
The Rhode Island Domestic Missionary Society was formed in 1802 and the Evangelical Consociation of Congregational Churches was formed in 1806. The two entities merged in 1912 as the Rhode Island Congregational Conference. The Rhode Island Congregational Conference merged with the Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference in 1931 to form the Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference. After the formation of the United Church of Christ, the conference was known as the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ. In 2020, the Rhode Island, Connecticut, and Massachusetts Conferences merged to form the Southern New England Conference of the United Church of Christ. This collection contains the records of the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ and its predecessor organization and includes meeting minutes, board records, reports, programs and brochures, newsletters, communications, and legal records.
United Church of Christ. Rhode Island Conference
Evangelical Consociation of Congregational Churches in Rhode Island
Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference
Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference.
Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference
Rhode Island Congregational Conference
Rhode Island Home Missionary Society
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Historic Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ in the 1970s, 1984, and February 2025; only the 2025 accrual has an accession number: 2025-04.
Historical Note
The organization of Congregationalists into a single statewide entity in Rhode Island began in 1802 with the formation of the Rhode Island Domestic Missionary Society. This group was closely followed up with the formation of the Evangelical Consociation of Congregational Churches in 1806. The first of these two groups became the Rhode Island Home Missionary Society in 1849 and became a centralized administrative group focused on the needs of Congregationalists within Rhode Island. The later of the two groups, which had a few names, but most prominently settled on the Rhode Island Congregational Conference, was initially formed to promote fellowship and communication between the ordained Congregational clergy of Rhode Island. The two organizations formally united as a single entity in 1912 while retaining the name Rhode Island Congregational Conference.
The Christians in Rhode Island largely belonged to one of two different conferences throughout the 19th century. The Connecticut Christian Conference was formed in 1821 and then in 1834 became the Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference. The Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference, formed in 1837, separated from the Massachusetts Christian Conference to form an explicitly anti-slavery Christian Conference. The Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference merged into the Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference in 1875. When the national Congregational and Christian organizations merged together in 1931, the Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference merged with the Rhode Island Congregational Conference to form the Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference.
After the formation of the United Church of Christ in 1957, the Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference became known as the Rhode Island Congregational Conference (United Church of Christ) after the Constitution was amended in 1963. Eventually, the name would become the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ.
A proposal for the Rhode Island, Connecticut, and Massachusetts Conferences of the United Church of Christ to merge was initially submitted in 2016. On January 1, 2020, the Southern New England Conference of the United Church of Christ was formed out of the merger of those three statewide conferences. Offices for the Historic Rhode Island Conference were subsequently closed and by 2025 the papers and records of the conference were appropriately disbursed to various organizations.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ. The collection is primarily administrative in nature and includes records, minutes, reports, financial records, board records, annual reports, and correspondence that speak to the day-to-day running of the conference. The collection also contains records of predecessor organizations, most prominently, the Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference, the Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference, and the Rhode Island Home Missionary Society. The collection also contains records related to the programs, task forces, and committees that the conference promoted and supported throughout its history. A sizable portion of the collection are communications and legal records related to individual Congregational and Christian churches within Rhode Island and their ministers.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged into the four series listed below. The Conference records series has been further divided into seven topical subseries to support the accessibility of the materials. Materials within most series and subseries have been further arranged into chronological order by start date. Materials within the Church communications and records series and the Conference programs and task forces series have been arranged according to chronological order to mimic how these materials were originally filed, or intended to be filed, by the original record keepers.
Series 1: Church communications and records, 1812-2019
Series 2: Christian conference records, 1827-1938
Series 3: Conference records, 1839-2019
Subseries 1: Financial records, 1839-2017
Subseries 2: Legal records, 1839-2017
Subseries 3: Administrative records, 1863-2018
Subseries 4: Ministerial records, 1923-1959
Subseries 5: Board of directors records, 1928-2019
Subseries 6: Conference history, 1945-1970
Subseries 7: Annual reports and meetings, 1948-2017
Series 4: Conference programs and task forces, 1930-2017
Technical Requirements
This collection contains both compact disks and floppy disks. Information on floppy discs cannot be retrieved and are unavailable to researchers. Researchers may access information from compact disks with the help and permission of a CLA staff member.
Related Materials
Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference Records, 1803-1973, MSS 140. Rhode Island Historical Society.
Charitable bequests.; Church correspondence.; Church property.; Church records and registers.; Clergy conferences.; Clergy -- Correspondence.; Home missions.; Social justice -- Religious aspects -- United Church of Christ.; Evangelical Consociation of Congregational Churches in Rhode Island; Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference; Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference.; Rhode Island Congregational Christian Conference; Rhode Island Congregational Conference; Rhode Island Home Missionary Society; United Church of Christ. Southern New England Conference; United Church of Christ. Rhode Island Conference
- Church communications and records, 1812 2019; 1812-2019; 1 Volume; 53 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records relating to various Congregational Churches in Rhode Island. The majority of the records are either direct communications between the conference and the individual churches and/or records related to church properties. Another large portion of the records are related to the hiring of ministers and the completion of church profiles as part of the hiring process. The series also contains various records and documents the churches sent to the conference over the course of their histories.
  - Amicable Congregational Church, 1928 2019; 1928, 1968-2019 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Armenian Evangelical Church, 1938 2017; 1938-2017 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Barrington Congregational Church, 1957 2019; 1957-2019 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Beneficent Congregational Church, 1932 1990; 1932-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Beneficent Congregational Church, 1991 2018; 1991-2018 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bliss Four Corners, 1955 1987; 1955-1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Broad Street Christian Church, 1875 1946; 1875-1946 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Central Falls Congregational Church, 1953 1959; 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Central Congregational Church, 1953 2018; 1953-2018 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chapel Street Congregational Church, 2011 2019; 2011-2019 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chepachet Union Church, 1946 2006; 1946-2006 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Church of Christ (Providence), 1812 1816; 1812-1816 (Box 8, Volume 2)
  - Clayville Christian Church, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Darlington Congregational Church, 1908 1970; 1908-1970 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Edgewood Congregational Church, 1964 2012; 1964-2012 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - First Christian Church of Rockland, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - First Congregational Church (Bristol), 1959-2007 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - First Korean Church, 1979 1987; 1979-1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - First Korean Church, 1990 2007; 1990-2007 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Four Corners Community Chapel, 1960 2007; 1960-2007 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Hope Church Congregational, 1952 2012; 1952-2012 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Hughesdale Congregational Church, 1930 1984; 1930-1984 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Iglesia Evangélica Hispana, 1981 2019; 1981-2019 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Irons Homestead dedication, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Kingston Congregational Church, 1956 2016; 1956-2016 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Knightsville-Franklin Congregational Church, 1963 2006; 1963-2006 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Laotian Evangelical Church, 1997 2011; 1997-2011 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon Larger Parish, 1951 2009; 1951-2009 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Newman Congregational Church, 1955 2012; 1955-2012 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Newport Congregational Church, 1974 2012; 1974-2012 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newport Congregational Church, 1980 2001; 1980-2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Newport Congregational Church renewal proposal, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Newport Congregational Church, 1984 1991; 1984-1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Newport Congregational Church lawsuit, 1990 1993; 1990-1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - North Congregational Church, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - North Congregational Church, 1912 1930; 1912-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oversized photographic prints of Rhode Island churches, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Park Place Congregational Church, 1961 2017; 1961-2017 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pawtucket Congregational Church, 1952 2009; 1952-2009 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Peace Dale Congregational Church, 1956 2015; 1956-2015 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Riverpoint Congregational Church, 1926 2018; 1926-2018 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Riverside Congregational Church, 1951 2011; 1951-2011 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Sayles Memorial Congregational Church, 1966 2009; 1966-2009 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Seekonk Congregational Church, 1968 2018; 1968-2018 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sheldon Street Church, 1949 2019; 1949-2019 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Slaterville Congregational Church, 1957 2019; 1957-2019 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Smithfield Avenue Congregational Church, 1958 2019; 1958-2019 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Union Congregational Church, 1889 1945; 1889-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - United Congregational Church (East Providence), undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - United Congregational Church (Little Compton), 1948 2014; 1948-2014 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - United Congregational Church (Newport), 1943 2011; 1943-2011 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - United Congregational Church (Westerly), 1960 2019; 1960-2019 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Woodridge Congregational Church, 1948 2011; 1948-2011 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Wood River Junction Church, 1931 1957; 1931-1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Christian conference records, 1827 1938; 1827-1938; 11 Volumes; 25 Folders
  This series contains records relating to the Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference and the Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference. The series largely contains administrative records from the two conferences, with the bulk of the series being meeting minutes. A sizable portion of the series is also correspondence files. The series also contains newsletters, bulletins, certificates, financial records, and certificates.
  - Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference minutes, 1827 1866; 1827-1866 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference minutes, 1835 1859; 1835-1859 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference minutes, 1843 1874; 1843-1874 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference minutes and reports, 1843 1874; circa 1843-1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1849 1850; 1849-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence of recess from sessions, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference executive board correspondence, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence of churches and certificates of delegates for session, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1854 1864; 1854, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rhode Island and Connecticut Christian Conference minutes, 1867 1875; 1867-1875 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference minutes, 1875 1905; 1875-1905 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Ministerial Association minutes and treasury records, 1876 1897; 1876-1897 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, circa 1877 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference executive board minutes, 1886 1897; 1886-1897 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference printed programs, 1890 1891; 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference executive board minutes, 1897 1905; 1897-1905 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference petition to license E. S. Greenleaf, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference, 1905 1913; 1905-1913 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference executive board minutes, 1905 1929; 1905-1929 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference quarterly bulletin, 1907 1925; 1907-1925 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference minutes, 1913 1927; 1913-1927 (Box 2, Volume 10)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference records, 1928 1933; 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rhode Island and Massachusetts Christian Conference certificates, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Conference records, 1839 2019; 1839-2019; 8 Volumes; 114 Folders
  This series contains records related to the administration and functions of the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ, as well as its predecessor and subordinate organizations. The series includes conference histories, ministerial correspondence, legal and financial records, governance documents, meeting minutes, board reports, annual reports, and conference planning records.
  - Financial records, 1839 2017; 1839-2017; 3 Volumes; 18 Folders
    This subseries contains financial records for the conference as well as organizations under the conference. The subseries contains ledgers, fund books, documents related to trusts and bequests, investment related records, financial statements, and other various types of financial records.
    - Rhode Island Home Missionary Society treasurer's books, 1839 1903; 1839-1903 (Box 8, Volume 1)
    - Ministerial Fund ledger, 1869 1932; 1869-1932 (Box 2, Volume 11)
    - Rhode Island Home Missionary Society ledger, 1914 1930; 1914-1930 (Box 2, Volume 12)
    - Ministerial Assistance Fund board records, 1922 2006; 1922-2006 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Investments and named funds, 1930 1975; 1930-1975 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Woman's Board of Missions named funds, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Ministerial Fund ledger, 1932 1939; 1932-1939 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Bequests, 1936 1977; 1936-1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Parsonage sale, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - List of holdings from the Rhode Island Congregational Conference to the Rhode Island Hopsital Trust Co agency account, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Investment committee records, 1968 1987; 1968-1987 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Hospital Trust National Bank guarantee, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Mabel T. Thornley bequest, 1971 1976; 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Consolidated fund records, 1978 2000; 1978-2000 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Annual church contribution goals, 1994 2001; 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Budget and finance committee records, 1995 1999; 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Financial statements, 1996 2013; 1996-1997, 2011-2013 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Waterman Trust affidavit, 2005 2011; 2005, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Finance and budget committee agenda, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Ministerial assistance fund records, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Ledger, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Legal records, 1847 1985; 1847-1985; 12 Folders
    This subseries contains legal records related to the conference. Much of the subseries contains deeds and other property related documents. The subseries also contains legal documents related to the government, legal agreements, and other various legal documents.
    - Legal records, 1847 1969; 1847-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 250 Waterman Street property records, 1900 1984; 1900-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Slatersville deeds, 1902 1969; 1902-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Petitions and decrees, 1908 1930; 1908-1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Edith M. May papers and agreement, 1911 1985; 1911-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous legal and property records, 1916 1985; 1916-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Plymouth-Union Congregational Church mortgage papers, 1918 1926; 1918-1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Academy Avenue property records, 1921 1926; 1921-1926 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Armenian Evangelical Church mortgage, 1928 1972; 1928-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Samuel Clarke Fund superior court decree, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Warwick church property records, 1957 1971; 1957-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Warwick papers, 1958 1970; 1958-1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Administrative records, 1863 2018; 1863-2018; 5 Volumes; 41 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the administration of the conference. The subseries contains records related to the organizations and structure of conference, such as constitutions, bylaws, and records related to potential and realized restructurings. The series also contains records and minutes related to organizations established under the conference, such as the Rhode Island Home Missionary Society, the Congregational Brotherhood of Rhode Island, and the Rhode Island Women's Fellowship. This subseries also contains records related to the formation of the Southern New England Conference, the successor to the Rhode Island Conference. The subseries includes meeting minutes, governance documents, planning document, and photographs.
    - Rhode Island Congregational Conference members, 1863 1950; 1863-1950 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Rhode Island Home Missionary Society records, 1876 1930; 1876-1930 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    - Foster Center Rhode Island correspondence, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Rhode Island Home Missionary Society "report of Greeks in Providence", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Rhode Island Congregational Association minutes, 1908 1928; 1908-1928 (Box 2, Volume 8)
    - Congregational Brotherhood of Rhode Island secretary book, 1910 1912; 1910-1912 (Box 2, Volume 9)
    - Rhode Island Congregational Conference records, 1912 1936; 1912-1936 (Box 3, Volume 6)
    - Proposed plan of union, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Rhode Island Home Missionary Society, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Harry B. Sherman photograph, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Rhode Island Fellowship of Congregational Christian Women board records, 1958 1988; 1958-1960, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Rhode Island Women's Fellowship board records, 1968 1984; 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Conference structure study, 1970 1980; 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Conference resolutions, 1971 2001; 1971-2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Human resources committee minutes, 1974 2003; 1974-2003 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Women's Fellowship records held by the conference, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Planning and resources commission communications and conference planning meetings, 1984 1991; 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Planning and resources commission minutes, 1987 1989; 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Planning and resources commission goals, 1987 1991; 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Planning and resources commission listening project, 1992 1993; 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - New England staff retreat records, 1988 2005; 1988-2005 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - New England staff retreat photographs, circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Conference covenant records, 1989 1993; 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Conference restructuring, 1992 1995; 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Personnel committee minutes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Leadership team meetings, 1994 1995; 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - By-laws, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Constitution, 1999 2004; 1999-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Conference yearbooks, 2003 2006; 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Conference directories, 2003 2008; 2003-2008 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Nominating committee records, 2004 2011; 2004-2011 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Conference staff meetings, 2008 2009; 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Compact disks, 2010 2017; 2010-2017 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - 11 year conference profile, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Ecclesiastical council records, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Church and ministry committee records, 2011 2015; 2011-2015 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Personnel policies, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 53)